[Music]
good evening and good day everyone
welcome to episode 27
of the ask a budget show and today we're
going to speak about
black holes and quantum mechanics and
artificial intelligence
and science so let's get right
into it my friends let's go for it with
question number one
so the first question is
according to quantum immortality
schrodinger's cat should live which of
these two concepts
is valid that's an interesting question
so let me uh explain what quantum
immortality is so it's a thought
experiment in quantum
mechanics so it there are several
interpretations of quantum mechanics as
i hope you are aware one of these the
most widely accepted one until very
recently has been the copenhagen
interpretation
which says that uh particle
superpositions basically
a particle remains in a superposition
until it is observed and
where it was before that is not
meaningful at all so don't ask questions
just calculate and get the results
that's the copenhagen interpretation
there are several others but one of the
important ones is the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics
which is uh due to hugh everett so
according to
this interpretation of quantum mechanics
every time an observation is made so
before an observation is made a particle
let's say
an electron is in a superposition of
states
the moment you observe it the
superposition the wave function
collapses
and it resolves itself in one place but
until then it was in many places at once
so according to the many worlds
interpretation every time you make a
measurement
the world line splits off into two
branches or several
branches possibly usually it's two and
the
the electron is in one place for you but
it's in various other locations
in another parallel universe
so that's the many world interpretation
so essentially it says that every time
you make
a decision a choice
every time you do that the world splits
your world line
splits into two branches so so
for exa for example it looks like this
so here it is so this is you
basically this is you and when you make
a choice
let's say you are flipping a coin so in
and you see the result is heads so this
is the result for you but in another
parallel universe you go to tails and
every time you flip a coin or make any
choice in your life
the world line keeps branching off into
into several
branches in this manner and eventually
it looks like this
after some time and eventually
over a longer period of time it looks
like this
you know your your world line branches
off in so many different branches
and this basically or for example this
this is the kind of decision tree and
world line that you
get branching world line every time you
make a choice so this
basically this image could represent
what you have done over one
maybe one day all the choices you made
in one day
they led off to the branching off of
your
world line into so many different
branches so basically it means that
there is an almost infinite number of
parallel universes in which you exist
based on the choices you have made in
your life so for example
try and remember remember a time when
you had a closed shave
maybe an accident or an illness in which
you barely survived or you
you got very lucky well according to
this theory there is a parallel word in
which you did not survive that
you know so so that is the entire
basics basis of the many worlds theory
that every time you make a choice every
time
something happens there is also
something else which would have happened
so the thought experiment is like this
let's say that you have a loaded gun
in which there are only two chambers and
one chamber has a bullet the other
chamber is
empty and you're playing russian
roulette with yourself
so you put the gun to your head and you
pull the trigger now let's say you get
lucky
and it was empty but in a parallel
universe
you got you were not lucky the word
because you made a choice of pulling the
trigger
so the your world line split into two
branches
and in one branch of the world line you
got lucky and there was nothing in the
in the chamber
in another one you did not get lucky you
got shot
and you died but your consciousness
doesn't exist anymore in the other world
it only exists here so every time you
basically
according to this theory every time you
play this game in one universe you will
die in one universe you'll survive
and your consciousness will always
remain in one universe so it will appear
to you
that you keep on getting lucky every
time you pull the trigger
so that is called quantum immortality
that every time a situ that you are put
in a situation where you may
live or die both these possibilities
will occur
in two different branches of the
universe or in two parallel universes
the universe will split off and your
consciousness will survive
in the world in which you have survived
but in a parallel world you will have
died
so according if you take this far enough
it means that you never die
no matter what happens you never die you
always get lucky because your
consciousness somehow
does survive in one branch of the
possibilities
of your world line and if you take it
far enough it means that no matter what
happens your consciousness will survive
even when your physical body is on the
point of dying it
somehow lingers on lingers and lingers
on and it seems to indicate
the many worlds in this this thought
experiment of quantum immortality
and this many world theory it kind of
seems to indicate that consciousness
your individual consciousness
essentially will survive forever
and therefore it means that you are
quantum mechanic mechanically immortal
basically it says that your
consciousness is local
it is local it is tied to this physical
body
but it will survive on somehow even if
you go into a coma
and everyone thinks you're dead or
whatever your consciousness lingers on
somehow
so that is quantum immortality now
let's talk about the cat showing your
scat so you place a cat in a box
and you give it half an hour you put
some something in there which will
either kill it or
let it live so the chance of the cat
living or dying
is 50 50. so every time you open the box
you will find that the cat is either
dead or alive
and when the box is closed and you don't
know what's inside it means the cat is
is in the super position of states dead
as well as alive
now according to quantum immortality the
question is the cat should survive it
should live right
but only from its perspective not from
my perspective
so if if i was the cat in the box then
from my perspective i will never die
of course i may die but in a parallel
universe
in which my consciousness no longer
survives so from my perspective
i keep on surviving but if i am an
external observer
and i am watching a cat then from the
cat's perspective there's always a world
in which it survives
but from my perspective it may have died
so it's all about perspective it's about
the perspective of the observer and the
person who's actually experiencing this
so from an external observer's
perspective the cat may die
50-50 but from the cat's perspective
from its own
world line it will always survive
so that is the concept of quantum
immortality it's a very interesting
concept
if the many worlds interpretation of
quantum mechanics is correct
then it essentially indicates that
your consciousness will survive forever
it may even
somehow transcend the death of your body
it may
it may look like that so it's a very
interesting concept in in
quantum mechanics the real debate is
whether this
theory this interpretation the many
worlds interpretation is correct or not
so there's an increasing number of
physicists
who are gravitating towards this concept
who believe that this concern this this
interpretation
the manuals interpretation is indeed the
correct interpretation of quantum
mechanics
so this debate is still out there it's a
matter of opinion
among physicists and
it's not yet proven because we still
don't understand quantum mechanics but
this
could be one of the possible
interpretations and possible ways
possible uh things that quantum
mechanics is trying to tell us
so that's a very interesting question to
start off with
okay avinash asks what is it like
inside a black hole
so let me tell you a story a fable
so once upon a time the butterflies
you know butterflies are fascinated with
the flame right
they love the flame butterflies and
moths like they like to go towards the
flame and
they somehow sometimes get killed by the
flame
so butterflies are fascinated with the
flame by the flame
so once upon a time the butterflies got
together
they organized a scientific conference
to discuss and try to
try to unravel the mystery of the flame
what is the flame
so the best butterfly minds got together
the best scientists theoreticians
experimentalists etc they came together
for a conference
and they all discussed and debated among
each other what is the flame
okay so after several hours one of the
young butterflies got tired he said i'm
gonna go and find out for myself
so one of the young butterfly scientists
he flew off he went towards the flame
he went very close to the flame almost
got burned
he came back he came back to the
conference and he explained what he
experienced so the wise old butterfly
who was the head of the conference he
said that very good thank you very much
very interesting but unfortunately we
have not really
uh we don't really have any new
information about the flame
so another young butterfly goes out he
says i'm gonna find out
so he goes he flies all the way to the
flame he even touches it gets burned
comes back and tells what happened once
again the wise old butterfly the
chairman of the conference he says
unfortunately even your experience
doesn't tell us anything new about the
flame
then a third butterfly goes to the flame
he flies to the flame
and he goes inside the flame and he gets
burned
so the butterflies from far away the
conference they're observing what
happened
so the wise old chairman the chair
butterfly
he says that yes so finally one of our
people
our young friend has finally understood
what the flame is
but unfortunately that information
only he knows it we will never know it
because he'll not be able to communicate
it back to us
so we my friends are these butterflies
and the black hole is the flame
so unless we have a black hole in a lab
or somewhere nearby and we can actually
go and observe it we
can't really tell what it's like inside
the black hole and if one of us were to
actually go inside a black hole
and find out what's inside we'll never
be able to come out and tell our friends
what's inside so
that is the truth of black holes we
don't know what's inside we have no
means of knowing what's inside
we don't have a black hole somewhere
nearby that we can go and observe
we have uh
observations of objects that appear to
be black holes
they seem to be abundant in the new in
the universe every
galaxy seems to have a supermassive
black hole at its center but what's
inside what's beyond the event horizon
we still
don't know because our physics breaks
down
inside the black hole uh general
relativity black
breaks down the curvature becomes
infinite density of mass and matter and
energy becomes infinite
it's called a singularity a singularity
indicates that your theory has broken
down it doesn't indicate there's an
actual
infinity in there so we don't know as of
now what's inside a black hole and that
is why black holes are such
a fascinating uh topic and that's why so
much research is being done to
unravel the mysteries of the black hole
and one of the possible ways of doing
this
is to try and reconcile
uh general relativity with
quantum mechanics and create a quantum
theory of gravity so that is
the big big audacious goal that we have
right now to
create to try and create a a quantum
theory of gravity
so that would possibly resolve and throw
some more light so to say
onto them onto the question of what's
inside the black hole as of today we are
not really sure
akash asks would we be able to
distinguish a black hole from a wormhole
if we discover it
is there any chance that some of the
black holes we have discovered are
actually wormholes
and what would a wormhole look like
that's a very interesting question so
black holes and wormholes are very
similar from
for an external observer at least from
from a distance they both
are extremely massive objects they
create
extreme distortions in space-time
the very strong gravitational fields and
and
that's why from a distance a wormhole
could very much look like a black hole
so a wormhole is essentially as a hole
in space-time
so in the three-dimensional world a hole
is a two-dimensional object isn't it
a hole has two dimensions in our world
so in a four-dimensional world
in four-dimensional space-time of a
whole would have three dimensions
so it would essentially a wormhole would
essentially be a spherical object
but unlike a black hole which is
completely dark
or completely transparent a wormhole
would know if you go
if you were to go close to wormhole it
would actually
you would actually be able to look
through it and see the other side
of what's on the other side of the
wormhole because a wormhole is
essentially a tunnel that
that connects two disparate regions of
space-time
so if you were to find a wormhole and if
you were to peer into it
you would be able to see what's on the
other side of the wormhole you know
in a region of space time that's really
far away so that's one difference
if you can go close close enough then
you would see that there is
something at the other end of the
wormhole if it were to be if it were to
be
uh if it were if it were to stay open
for a long period of time
which would allow you to observe the
second thing is that the question is
that
is there any chance some of the black
holes we have discovered are actually
wormholes that's a very interesting
question
so a wormhole let's say you have a
supermassive wormhole let's say that one
of the
uh supermassive black holes at the
center of a galaxy is actually a
wormhole okay
so what would uh
what would the uh phenomena be like
around this wormhole so essentially a
wormhole if it were to be a traversable
vermole it means that matter can fall
inside
the wormhole right and
because of the extreme gravitational
field that the supermassive vermont
would have
that matter that falls inside would be
accelerated to relativistic velocities
extremely high speeds
a significant percentage of the speed of
light so it would be very very
moving very fast extremely fast
and matter from the other side of the
tunnel would also be falling into the
wormhole at extremely
high speeds so it's there is a
significant possibility
that matter that is falling inside from
both the ends of the wormhole
would actually collide in the throat of
the wormhole
and this could give rise to enormous
explosions inside
which would spew matter outside again so
extremely
highly energetic uh gamma rays and
radiation etc would come out of this
wormhole
and we do see such phenomena it's called
quasars
quasars are active galactic nuclei uh
what's believed is that these are
supermassive black holes with an
extremely
massive accretion disk around them and
it is the in-falling matter of this
accretion disk
that causes all these extreme jets
to be spewed out of this black hole
and that's why it is so luminous for
example a quasar would have a luminosity
of several times
of several times the entire luminosity
of our own galaxy the milky way
so that's how luminous these quasars are
so if this was a
wormhole in which matter is falling
inside from both ends
then it could conceivably give rise to a
similar phenomenon
so it is definitely possible that
these quasars these active galactic
nuclei
may possibly be wormholes instead of
black holes it is
certainly a possibility and it is a
possibility that is
i think it is being taken quite
seriously
so as of today we don't unless we have
a wormhole nearby that we can actually
go and observe
unless we have that we can't really tell
but from the mathematics of the the
physics that we know from the physics
that we know
we it is quite it's quite clear that
these are very similar objects at least
from a distance
but there are certain phenomena that we
can predict and if we can find
signatures of
those phenomena for example extremely
energetic gamma rays
then it would indicate possibly that
there's a wormhole there
instead of a supermassive black hole so
i think it's a
it's an it's an area of active research
as we speak
okay ishaan asks how can light have
momentum
if it has no mass is there a problem in
the equation of momentum that is p
equals mv well light has momentum and we
get this from
very basic quantum mechanics so let me
i hope you're not very scared of math
because i'm going to show you some math
hang on let one second it's a very
simple
derivation let me
okay let's remove this all right here we
are so do photons and momentum so we
know that
from einstein's famous equation
e equals m c squared if you can see the
equation number one here e equals m
squared so uh mass is equivalent to
energy energy is equivalent to mass
now in case of a photon which is light
we know that
it has no mass but it has a frequency
and the
relationship between frequency energy
energy is equals
hf where h is the planck constant so the
frequency
tells you what energy the photon has
now we know that h f equals m c squared
by combining these two equations
equations one two one and two
so we get this relationship h f equals m
c squared
you rearrange that you get m equals h f
by c squared so the
photon has a relativistic mass of sorts
an equivalent mass which is given by h
planck constant
multiplied by the frequency of the
photon divided by
the square root of the speed of light
the square of the speed of light
now as you said the equation of momentum
in classical physics is p
equals mv where v is the velocity of the
particle
in the case of the photon v the speed
speed or velocity is the speed of light
so we put v equals t
and by combining these equations we get
p equals h
f by c but in quantum mechanics we know
that the frequency is
equal to the speed of light divided by
the wavelength of the photon
and by putting all that together we get
this relationship the equation nine
which is p equals h over lambda which
means that the
momentum of a photon is equal to the
planck constant divided by the
wavelength of the photon
and this is why this is how we know that
photons
have momentum and this is experimentally
observed
so that is a very simple straightforward
derivation
of the momentum of a photon it's a
simplistic derivation but
i think it illustrates very well why
photons have momentum so there is no
problem in any equation of momentum such
of a momentum etc it's all perfectly
valid
okay anu mitha asks can you please
explain the theory of quantum mechanics
that tells us that the world is an
illusion
well quantum mechanics is strange and
weird etc
it doesn't really tell us that the world
is an illusion it tells us that there is
something
deeper there is a deeper underlying
reality
that that lies beyond what we can
actually
observe so the best theory that we have
of the ultra microscopic quantum world
is actually called quantum
field theory and according to the
quantum field theory the best theory
that we have
which explains the world in
extraordinary precision
so according to quantum field theory
there are no particles particles are an
illusion
even vacuum even the vacuum of space is
an illusion so yeah you could say that
the world is an illusion
the particles are actually local
manifestations
of fields of infinite fields
so in the standard model of physics you
have 17 known particles
okay and these essentially are the
manifestations of 17 different
fields so all the
uh light that we see its photons
which are excitations in the
electromagnetic field
the electrons that make up our body and
everything
that we know these are manifestations of
the electron field
okay these are local manifestations of
the infinite electron field that
permeates the entire universe
then the the protons and neutrons that
are in our body and in the world
which make everything up these are
composed of up quarks and down
quarks so these are manifestations of
the up up quark field in the down quark
field
so these 17 fields
permeate the entire universe it's just
so the electrons
that make up the world that we know that
are a part of the world that we know
they are basically part of the same
field that permeates the entire universe
the same electron field
so the fee the electrons in my body are
part of the same field
electron field that are that give rise
to the electrons in your body or
wherever you're sitting
etc so this is quantum field theory so
this is the
the more fundamental underlying reality
of the world
so yeah in a way the world that we see
is an over simplification that our
senses make so that we can make sense of
the universe
because the reality actually is much
more complex that one than what we
perceive it's like you have a cell phone
and when you open the cell phone and you
you can send an email etc by clicking on
some icons etc
and the interface the graphical user
interface of your cell phone
it hides the complexity that's really in
there all the circuits and voltages and
the zeros and ones and the layers of
softwares and algorithms
and all that if you had to toggles one
if you had to toggle once and zeros and
if you had to toggle voltages
to send an email you would never be able
to send an email
so your cell phone's graphical user
interface
over simplifies the world to me to help
you make sense of it
and similarly our sensory organs
they oversimplify the world so that we
can actually make sense of it otherwise
it would be too complicated
and it would need too much processing
power in orange
to cognitively observe it and process it
and make sense of it in real time
so the reality is much more complicated
and what we see is you could say
essentially an illusion
colors are an illusion everything is an
illusion we actually are made up of
fields interacting fields fields that
interact with each other
and give rise to the interactions the
four main the four
known forces and maybe some other ones
too who knows
so that in short is quantum field theory
it does tell us that the world is kind
of an illusion we are actually
all composed of fields even vacuum is
not vacuum it's not really empty
it's teeming with quantum fluctuations
which obey heisenberg's uncertainty
principle so
the world is really way more complex
than we can ever imagine
so that in brief anumita is quantum
field theory which kind of tells us that
the world that we
see is actually an illusion
mayank asks is it possible that we are
living
in a black hole is it possible that a
black hole
has eaten us and we are inside it
and also is it possible that every black
hole contains
an entire universe around it so this is
a question that many physicists have
taken up seriously in the past
that it it may be possible that black
holes could contain a baby
a black hole could possibly contain a
baby universe inside it
because we don't know what lies beyond
the event horizon
so it is conceivable that there could be
if you have a large enough black hole it
could essentially have
an entire universe inside it it is
conceivable but
so so let's consider the possibility
that our universe is essentially
is actually the inside of a black hole
of an enormous
black hole so is it is this consistent
with what we know about
the universe and the laws of physics so
we know that
uh that the universe has a temperature
there is an average temperature of the
universe which is about two point
something
kelvin which is extremely cold it's just
barely above
absolute zero so this is the temperature
of the cosmic microwave background
radiation that permeates the entire
universe so and
we know that there are black holes super
massive black holes that are colder than
this
and they are smaller so that
so basically if you we know that black
holes have a temperature
and based on the temperature of black
hole we can determine the radius of the
black hole and the
volume and area of a black hole it's all
interrelated
right the radius of the short shield
radius is 2 mg by c squared where m
is the mass of the black hole g is
gravitational newton's gravitational
constant and c is the speed of light
2 mg divided by c squared that is the
radius schwarzschild radius of a black
hole
and the mass is proportional to the
temperature of a black hole
so we can calculate the
temperature of a black hole from the
radius and vice versa we can calculate
the radius of a black hole from the
temperature
now if you had a black hole which had
the temperature of
our universe then it would be much
smaller the calculation shows that
it would be much smaller than the radius
that the than the
size of the observable universe it would
be very much smaller than that so this
is one inconsistency that we have
that for a temperature of two point
something kelvin you get a
reasonably small black hole not
something that's bigger than the
observable universe that is the first
inconsistency
and the second inconsistency is that we
know that the universe is expanding
it's expanding now black holes don't
expand
right unless there is something inside a
black hole only a certain region of
space inside a black hole that expands
we don't know that right so there is
another inconsistency that our universe
is actually expanding we know it's exp
we have observed it we are aware of the
fact that expanding we have
this is proven by by uh observational
evidence
but black holes don't expand so once
again this is an inconsistency
so there are inconsistencies
uh if you try to assume that we are
inside a black hole and
the universe is the interior of a black
hole whose temperature is two point
whatever kelvin so it doesn't look like
the universe is the inside of a black
hole but it may be possible that the
small black holes that we have
even supermassive ones may contain a
universe of some kind
inside them it is possible but most
likely the universe that we
live in is not the interior of a black
hole
from the best information and knowledge
that we have
akash asks how did we determine the
planck length
and that it's the absolute smallest
length
considering that our understanding of
quantum mechanics is far from perfect
how can we be so sure about it
this is a very excellent question a
fundamental question
so okay i'll i it's better that i show
you so i share a screenshot with you
which would make more sense
one second here we have this
let me remove this question for a minute
so the question is how do we
how did we determine the planck length
as the smallest length
so we have four fundamental i'm sorry
not this one
the next one here we are okay so we have
four fundamental constants
of nature four fundamental physical
constants
first one is the speed of light in
vacuum which is this one here
three hundred thousand meters per second
or whatever it is here
then you have the planck constant of the
reduced planck constant h
cross equals h upon 2 pi which has this
value here
then you have the gravity so the speed
of light in vacuum is the universal
speed limit in the universe the planck
constant is what
is the constant that relates the energy
of a photon
with its frequency or wavelength then
you have the gravitational constant
which has this value
which essentially is a is a measure of
the strength of the gravitational
interaction and then you have the
boltzmann constant over here
which you can see which essentially
relates
the average kinetic energy or of the
particles in a gas
with the thermodynamic temperature of
that gas so these are the four
fundamental physical constants
and by combining these constant in
constants in a variety of ma
in a variety of ways we can come up with
units
which are called the planck units which
are the planck length the planck mass
planck time planck energy and planck
temperature
so so the planck length is the square
root of h cross g
upon c cubed and if you calculate that
it gives you the dimension
of of meters
it's it's a length and it is of the
order of 10 raised to minus 35
meters so that is how it has been
calculated it is the smallest length
that we can calculate so let's try and
imagine
what what the planck length actually
feels like right
so if if an atom if a hydrogen atom was
the size of the earth
then the planck length would be smaller
than an atom it would be
maybe smaller than even an electron
right
so that's how small the planck length is
so like i said we have these four
fundamental constants of nature
these ones here the four top you know
these four ones here
that define these four constants of
nature that define the properties of
space-time
they define the fundamental properties
of the universe
and the nature that we live in so the
planck length
is currently the best currently known
minimum length in the universe okay it
is
and it is the smallest length at which
gravity the force of gravity
can have any effect and in loop quantum
gravity
it is the scale the minimum scale or the
only scale at which space time itself is
quantized
and in string theory it is the scale
of strings so it is so basically
the significance is that in quantum
mechanics
according to the laws of quantum
mechanics it is impossible
to determine the position of a particle
to a precision smaller than the planck
length
that's another example of the uh
significance of the planck length
basically in physics in known physics
a length smaller than the planck length
is essentially meaningless it is
unphysical
so the planck length essentially is the
fundamental
limit of the resolution of the universe
the universe's the universe is pixelated
at the plank length
so that is the significance that is how
we have derived the planck length and
that is how we know that it is the
as of today with the laws of physics
physics that we know today
it is the smallest length that is
possible
in the in the known universe
okay so it is possible that in the
future we may actually be able to
uh understand the world better the
universe better
and we may find something smaller than
the plank length it is
certainly possible so here's the
question right
it's certainly possible if you can
reconcile gravity and quantum
mechanics then we may be perhaps able to
find something smaller than that
but as of today this is the smallest
resolution at which the universe makes
any sense
okay aditya asks what is the black hole
information paradox excellent question
the black hole information loss paradox
is essentially an
inconsistency between quantum
theory quantum mechanics quantum field
theory etcetera and general relativity
so uh let's take a look at let's say
let's look at
look at it like this we know that black
holes radiate it's called hawking
radiation
and we find out that this happens when
we combine quantum field theory and
general relativity
we we kind of combine it there's a semi
classical calculation
which gives rise to hawking radiation so
hawking radiation the radiation of black
holes
is thermal radiation which means that
its temperature determines
which means that the temperature of a
black hole determines the average
energy of these particles these
particles of radiation
and this is called black body radiation
it's completely random the only thing we
know about it
is the temperature and it entirely
depends on
the black hole's radius which is
proportional to the mass and the black
hole's temperature
which is also proportional to the mass
etc okay so that's
about hawking radiation it is thermal
radiation it is
it depends on the properties of a black
hole which is essentially three things
the mass of the black hole the angular
momentum of the black hole
and the charge of the black hole all
right so this
hawking river radiation essentially
tells you that black holes have a
temperature
they radiate away and because they
radiate this radiation
they shrink in size they shrink in size
and because the shrink in size their
mass decreases
their uh radius decreases
right and the
uh temperature backhoe is inversely
proportional to the mass of the black
hole
so as the mass decreases the temperature
rises
so black holes get hotter as they shrink
and as they get hotter they radiate
faster so they shrink even faster
so this is called black hole evaporation
now this is an irreversible process the
initial state of the black hole
so let's say we have a black hole inside
a box and we collect all the radiation
that comes out of it
so at the end of the evaporation process
there's no black hole left there's only
radiation in a box now this hawking
radiation is irreversible
which means that you cannot determine
the initial state of the black hole
from the final state which is the
radiation you can have many initial
states let's say a black hole
swallowed 17 stars and became this big
and then it radiated away
but from the radiation we cannot tell
that it followed 17 stars
it could have swords 27 smaller stars or
three bigger stars and
become a black hole of the same size
right
so many initial states of the black hole
can give rise to this final state of
radiation so this
hawking radiation is an irreversible
process which is a huge problem in
quantum physics because in quantum
mechanics
processes are always time reversible
in principle at least which means that
one initial state gives rise to one
final state that's a one-to-one
correspondence between a final state and
an initial state
and this inconsistency is called the
black hole information
paradox right so uh it is
hoped or believed that quantum gravity
or theory of quantum gravity
a quantized theory of gravity will
hopefully resolve
this inconsistency between quantum
mechanics and general relativity
and uh perhaps solve the black hole
information loss paradox
uh maybe it's possible that black holes
don't evaporate completely and they
leave behind plank cons or planck mass
remnants
that are stable and maybe the
information stays
encoded in these plant mass remnants
perhaps that is one theory
or maybe there's even a theory that this
information that is lost
it is lost only in our universe but it
is
perhaps preserved in another another
universe
it is preserved somewhere in the
multiverse so these are theories or
speculations that may possibly
resolve the black hole information
paradox as of today we don't know
what is the resolution maybe it is
unsolvable but
that in short my friends is the black
hole information
loss paradox good question
okay arijit asks what will be the future
of
humanity if if a black hole is going to
eat the whole universe
where will humanity go or will
everything come to an end
that's a good question what if there's
an enormous black hole
outside of our universe which eats our
universe
well we don't know how large our
universe is
the universe that we can actually
observe is about
90 billion light years in
diameter and the actual universe
is most likely even larger than that it
may even be in finite
so can we have a black can first of all
we don't know if there's anything
outside the universe
and if there is a black hole outside the
universe which were to
absorb our universe then most likely it
would take
an infinite number of amount of time
firstly
and secondly it would be so big that we
would not even know about it
right because it would have to be larger
than the observable universe or maybe
it's smaller but then in that case it
would take an infinite amount of time
to swallow our universe so it's a
hypothetical question most likely if
if our universe were to be absorbed by a
black hole we would
most likely not even come to know
divyanshu asks
shortly after the big bang the
fundamental forces of the universe
split up as the universe cooled down
symmetry breaking yeah
how did this happen and if we can
achieve the temperatures at which this
symmetry breaking
happened can we unify the fundamental
force again
excellent question so
the best theory that we have as of today
that describes the evolution of the
universe
is the big bang theory like you said now
this theory is
basically describes it attempts to
reconstruct
the history of the universe what
happened at what time
it doesn't tell us how it happened it
tells it tries to tell us it tries to
reconstruct
what happened what were the different
phases in the evolution of the universe
but it doesn't try to reconstruct how it
happened why it happened
so we don't know why the four
fundamental forces
split up what made this happen what
caused the big bang
we don't know we as of today we don't
know any about anything about this
but i can tell you about the uh about
the very early universe which is a very
interesting
epoch in the evolution of our of our
history so to say
so first of all in the very very early
universe
right after the big bang you had
something called the planck
epoch so the planck epic is
basically the age the
history of the universe at a time
shorter than 10 raised to minus 43
seconds
so after the big bang before 10 raised
to minus 43 seconds have elapsed
that is called the planck epic
so during the planck epic it is believed
that all four
fundamental forces which is
electromagnetism the strong nuclear
force the weak nuclear force and
gravitation these four fundamental
forces they were all combined together
into one single fundamental force so
this
is the planck epoch when the universe
was at nearly the planck temperature
which is 10 raised to 32
kelvin which is an unimaginable
temperature
right so this was a very short epoch up
to 10 raised to minus 43 seconds in the
life of the universe
when all four forces were combined into
one
then you have the so-called grand
unification epic
in which gravity decouples so gravity
has deep
decoupled from the four forces and only
three forces remain together
which is in in a single combined force
called the electro nuclear force
so this grand unification effect is
between 10 raised to minus 43 seconds
and 10 raised to minus 36 36 seconds
after the big bang
it is that small window of time so
three forces are together one has
decoupled you have the electro nuclear
force
the grand unification temperature is
higher than 10 raised to 27 kelvin
okay to come to get an idea of that
the temperature of the sun surface of
the sun is about 5800 kelvin
and the temperature of the core of the
sun is about 15 16 million kelvin
which is 16 times 10 raised to 6 kelvin
and the temperature of a supernova is of
the order of 10 raised to 11 kelvin
so the grand unification temperature is
of the order it is greater than it was
greater than 10 raised to 27 kelvin
so 16 orders of magnitude higher than
the
hotter than the temperature of a
supernova so that's the kind of
conditions we had in the universe when
the three forces were together
gravity had already decoupled so
we don't know how it happened we don't
know how the symmetry breaking happened
how the forces decoupled etc as the
universe cooled down
but it is believed that we can achieve
if we can
actually achieve those temperatures then
we can unify the fundamental forces
again
now it is not physically possible
because the
highest temperature we can achieve on
earth in the lab is
nothing compared to 10 raised to 27
kelvin or even the planck temperature 32
kelvin
the temperature of a supernova is 16
orders of magnitude
lower than the grand unification
temperature
our best bet is theoretical physics
theoretical physics will be where is
what is hopefully going to
help us understand these forces more and
hopefully
help us uh construct a theory or
discover
the so-called theory of everything in
which we have a single equation
that describes all four forces
so so yeah that's the answer
we it is not possible to uh to have
these temperatures in a lab it is
beyond beyond the wildest dreams in the
realm of possibility all we can do is uh
we can use
our intellect and theoretical physics to
try and reconstruct
the the fundamental force which
unified all four forces from which every
other force was born
so that is what we hope hopefully it
will happen
someday in the future
they just asks what is the god particle
and why does it matter
so this is a this is a
name that has been given by the media
it's not scientists who have given
it the name the god particle it is
journalists who have called it the god
particle all right
so uh so this theory uh
emerged in the 1960s it was peter higgs
who proposed that there is an additional
boson
in the standard model the 17th boson
that imparts mass to matter
so we know that i have discussed this
before even today that
we have this theory the best theory
theory we know of is called quantum
field theory
in which you have the entire universe is
made up of interacting fields 17
different fields
so in the 1960s it was not known how the
universe gets
mass so peter higgs proposed that there
is a boson
a gauge boson whose field
interacts with the other fields in the
universe the 16 other fields in the new
in the universe
and it is the strength of the
interaction of these fields
that imparts mass to particles to these
fields
so for example the electromagnetic field
whose quantum is the photon doesn't
interact with this higgs field
and therefore the photon has no mass
now the weak field the the um
the neutrino field interacts very weakly
there are three kinds of neutrons so
there are three fields associated with
those
now these neutrino fields interact very
weakly
with the higgs field and that's why
neutrinos are very small masses
and the up quark down quark other fields
they interact more strongly
with the higgs field and therefore they
have higher masses
so it is the strength of the interaction
of these fields
of the 16 other fields with the higgs
field that determines how much
mass those the quanta of those fields
have
so that is the so-called higgs field
the so-called god particle so the
quantum of the higgs field is the higgs
boson
and that is what is popularly known
as the higgs boson why does it matter
because without it there would be no
mass in the universe
so it is the field and the particle that
imparts
mass to the universe without this
particle in this field this universe
would have no mass
and life as we know it would not exist
so that is the significance of the higgs
boson
and the higgs field
animal asks how to mitigate
problems like algorithm bias
bias in artificial intelligence this is
a very good question
so we believe that artificial
intelligence is a god-like phenomenon
which knows everything etc well that is
not true
artificial intelligence is essentially
something that emerges mostly
well there are a number of ways to immer
to to
construct or create artificial
intelligence one of the ways is machine
learning
in which you have in which you have an
algorithm which is fed
data it and it learns on its own based
on pattern recognition etc
and that is how it develops its own
so-called
intelligence it learns on its own it is
sometimes supervised learning sometimes
it's unsupervised learning etc
but you you find that these algorithms
they learn on their own for example you
have these chess playing algorithms
that basically learn how to play chess
by playing lots of chess games against
themselves
or by going through a great amount of
data of
hundreds of thousands of chess games
that were played in the past
so it learns on its own the rules of
chess and then it can
start defeating human players now you
have these other algorithms like
language recognition algorithms
automatic translation algorithms
and text generator algorithms which are
able to
generate text based upon certain
keywords that you input
and it gives you very human readable
text it looks like it's been written by
human beings
so this is basically the thing we're
talking about and
this is where algorithm bias comes in
so algorithm bias is it occurs in a
variety of ways
first of all you may have a faulty
algorithm
an algorithm that produces results that
are systematically biased
or prejudiced because of erroneous
assumptions in the machine learning
process
which could arise from faulty or poor or
inaccurate data yeah because if garbage
goes in garbage comes out you know this
is the old adage in computer science
gi go garbage garbage out so if you have
data that is inaccurate it is poor it is
biased in some manner
it is not representative of the entire
population etc for example that's what
happens
or you can have problems introduced by
people who design
and train the machine learning system
who create algorithms
that reflect either unintended cognitive
biases of theirs
or actually real life prejudices right
for example i have seen this myself you
have this gpt
3 uh text generation
uh artificial intelligence basically
and if you input keywords related to
india into it it outputs text that looks
like it has been written by
marxists hindu phobic texts that reflect
certain kinds of biases against india
so it is because these people who have
been training the algorithm when it
comes to india related subject matter
they have been basically feeding it
texts that have been written by leftist
and marxist academics and left-oriented
uh journalistic publications it's very
clear so whenever you input something
related to india
keywords related to india into gpd3 it
gives you
it outputs you paragraphs of text
that look like they have been written by
some professor in jnu
jawaharlal nehru university so that is a
clear
demonstration of algorithm bias so
either these biases are created by
poor data or data that is prejudiced or
it is slanted in a certain ideological
or cultural direction it either uh
reflects real life prejudices of certain
people of the people who are introducing
the data
or unintended cognitive biases or biases
that are introduced by
incomplete or faulty or prejudicial or
biased
data sets to train and validate
these machine learning systems so that
is algorithm bias
so so you have to address the real
reason why this
bias has occurred either it is a
faulty algorithm or it is data that is
not representative
of the entire t of knowledge about that
particular thing
for example in the case of india if you
feed only data that comes from
left-leaning journalistic organizations
or
leftist marxist professors then the
machine learning algorithm will get
trained on that
and every time you give it keywords
related to india it's going to give you
output
that looks like it's been produced by
jnu professors
so that is what algorithm bias is so the
mitigation is
it depends on how it has been introduced
prietam asks can ai really
develop consciousness and should we
worry about it
we should not worry about ai developing
consciousness let me tell you why
consciousness is a very
is a very complicated phenomenon we
don't even have a proper scientific
definition of consciousness
let me try and conjure up a definition
of consciousness right here on the spot
so what is consciousness what is a
conscious
system in my opinion i would say that a
conscious system is a physical entity
which essentially stores
a snapshot of the external world within
itself and it's able to cognitively
process that
and come up with scenarios and
opinions about the external world so
it's a system that contains a snapshot
of data
which comes in via sensory mechanisms
about the external world and it's able
to actually
uh it's able to recognize that it is
separate from the external world
and it is self-conscious which means it
is conscious of itself
of its of its own being separate from
the external world
so it's a very complicated matter right
and it's not easy for any system to
become conscious first of all it would
need
sensory inputs that
evolve in such a way that it
it is able to get the whole gamut of
sensory inputs not just what somebody
else is inputting into it
so as of today ai systems
do have some input but that input is
determined solely by the people
who have developed the ai so they give
it data
that they decide that they curate
and these ais don't have access to the
world the way we do
they don't have eyes they don't have
access to
various other sources of sensory data so
it's very hard
given these limitations for an ai system
to develop
anything that that would come close to
human consciousness
and even if it were to become self-aware
what would it do with it
because a human being when it becomes
self-aware at the age of six months or
something
it takes 15-20 years for it to become a
useful human being who can actually
make some changes or some impact have
some impact on the world
so it's very hard for an ai it's it's
to to reach that level
because first of all ai's are designed
by us the neural network etc
and so because of all these factors and
because of the limitations of the
technology
and because they can be switched off
anytime etc we don't really have to
worry about it what we have to worry
about
is the intelligent humans who use the ai
who have developed the ai for certain
purposes and who are using the ai
because see ai is a technology
technology is always a force multiplier
in the stone age we had sticks and
stones which did multiply the
force that you you could give as a punch
now you had a stick or a stone which
gave you much more force
and which made you which helped you
exert that force or influence at a
distance so there was a force multiplier
then you now
we have guns and missiles and rockets
which are enormous for force multipliers
and with the emergence of ai
technologies we have an even
greater level of force multiplication so
now it's very easy for you to influence
somebody across the world if you have
access to ai systems
so we need to worry about the people who
are developing ai
we don't have to worry about ai
developing consciousness that is a very
far-fetched scenario i don't see it
happening
anytime in the near future not in the
next 20 20 30 years
any significant form of consciousness
but ai is already a very powerful
tool in the arsenal of of countries like
the united states and china and
and whoever else is developing it so it
is that
what we need to worry about it can
unleash a new age of colonialism digital
colonialism
we can all become digital slaves of
these powerful ai nations
which is why india needs to to to wake
up from its deep slumber and start
taking ai machine learning quantum
computing all these technologies
seriously that is what we need to worry
about people who
wield the ai that is the real threat to
humanity
harshit asks if ai is affecting
countries economy
or employment percentage then why
developing countries like ours are
chasing ai
or even for that matter why are
developing developed countries like u.s
china et cetera chasing ai
that will not affect employment do we
really need ai okay that's a good
question audrey so the thing is this
like i said ai is a force multiplier it
makes you way more powerful than what
you are
who doesn't want power it is
the inherent nature of humanity to chase
power
power trumps everything power trumps
wealth the moment you have
extraordinary power you control the
world that
is why they are pursuing ai
see any new technology that has been
developed in the past 100 200 500 years
it's only been used to enrich and
empower
countries and people
and militaries it's the first use of any
technology any powerful technology has
always been in the service
of the military which is controlled by a
powerful organization like a country
or a monarchy or a dictatorship or
whatever it is
that is why now we have corporations
so we have these big corporations in the
u.s that
are now uh the owners of very powerful
ai systems but those
corporations are under
someone's power aren't they they are
under the u.s government's
jurisdiction they are
the power lies somewhere else so they
these
corporations are tools in someone's
arsenal
and that arsenal can be that these tools
can be used for regime change
they can be used to influence them the
hearts and minds of people worldwide to
shape opinions
to effect regime change to to overthrow
certain governments
to install certain people in power it's
very easy now with ai
so that is why ai is being developed yes
it will take over jobs and make people
and and exacerbate the class divide in
capitalistic countries it may even uh
lead to great job losses in india who
cares
the people who ai empowers don't care
about this
haven't you seen the history of the
world in the past 500 years
it's all been about imperialism and
colonialism and it
would be very greatly mistaken to think
that
to think that imperialism and
colonialism is a thing of the past
it is not a thing of the past we are
still living in an imperial and colonial
age
and we may be upon the threshold of a
new age of digital colonization
and digital imperialism and many
and the countries that do not develop
that the countries that do not have the
foresight to start
developing ai capabilities of their own
they are the ones who will become the
digital coolies of the world
so india is currently going in the
direction because i don't see any
development
of any significance either in artificial
intelligence
machine learning neural networks super
computing
distributed computing
quantum computing anything of that sort
we are just consuming the products that
the west is giving us
which is something that needs to change
very quickly very soon
all right two questions why doesn't
israel have its own
space station only three countries
possess
space stations the us russia and
china and secondly why doesn't israel do
manned missions
well isro is not a decision-making body
isro is a pool of scientists they are
told
it is run by bureaucrats who and it is
run by the government of india
the bureaucrats are the one who once who
are in charge of all the
budget and everything they are the ones
who really control the the body on a
day-to-day basis
who do the micro management and all that
and the scientists
basically they do what they are told and
they are given a certain budget
and they have to follow directions and
obey orders
so the the reason why israel doesn't do
all this thus far hasn't done all this
thus far
is because the government of india has
never had the ambition to make india
great
space power india doesn't seem to have
that sort of ambition
yes there is a manned mission in the in
the working right now
it was supposed to be launched this year
i think
but because of koved everything has been
shut down
i don't see the chinese being shut down
the chinese space program being shut
down by kovid
i don't see spacex being shut down by
kovid but isro has been shut down by
kovid
everything has been pushed back two or
three years or whatever it is it is
extremely disappointing to say the least
that we have this
lackadaisical attitude towards
scientific progress and development
so it is because of this lack of
political will and
lack of political ambition that isro is
lagging behind
we have the best scientists in the world
but they
are not allowed to unleash their full
creativity and energy
in the direction that they should so yes
we will have a manned mission maybe in
the next year or two
we will demonstrate that we have the
technology of sending people into space
maybe 30 or 40 years in the future we
may have a small space station somewhere
hopefully not hopefully sooner so isro i
mean
somebody in the government had recently
made a statement that india
aims to have its own space station no
time frame was given
so that's the situation right now it is
entirely to a lack of political will
and political ambition and a lack of
political
foresight so isro has the capability to
to do a manned mission
and to create a speech to construct a
space station i wish
we would get more serious about space
because in the 21st century
the two or three nations who will lead
the world
in space explorations are the two or
three nations that will decide
the future of every human being on the
planet so it is for india to decide
whether we want to be the ones making
the decisions
or whether we want to be the ones doing
what we are told
so that is for india's political
leadership
to look into that is the decision they
need to make
abhishek asks a dog breeds 45 times per
minute and dies at the age of 25.
dogs usually live up to the age of 15
actually a turtle breeds four times per
minute and leaves
to the age of 300 years well some
thought of his daughter says
i think the galapagos started just live
uh
beyond a century or two yeah a human
being breeds 15 to 18 times per minute
and dies at the age of 80. can you
explain by controlling your breath
legend says that one can extend
extend life once life manifold
are there any contradictions so let me
give you another example
whales let's take the blue whale
the blue whale can can hold its breath
for
up to an hour or two hours underwater
and blue whales breathe maybe once or
twice a minute when they are on the
surface
so by this uh by this uh
by the logic that you provided a blue
whale should be able to live 500 years
or a thousand years but
blue whales live about 80 years or maybe
100 years
similarly dolphins also can hold their
breath for a very long period of time
they breathe a couple of times a minute
or two three times a minute
uh the large dolphins orcas so-called
killer whales in popular culture
they also can hold their breath for a
very long period of time
but they also don't live beyond 50 60 70
years
so there isn't a real pattern here
one can give many significant counter
examples especially the ones i just gave
but it is believed i don't know if there
have been any any proper
scientific studies about this it is
definitely possible that
by controlling your breath you achieve a
greater control
over your cardiovascular system and it
may it will definitely have
significant health benefits we know that
pranayama the practice of
pranayama has very significant health
benefits we also know that eating less
eating like 20
less can extend your lifespan by 20
years or 20 percent
so there are these things there are
these uh
this wisdom that has been passed on
especially in india for
thousands of years so it is time that
indian scientists
should do detailed proper long-term
studies about this and only then will be
able to
really know in a quantifiable scientific
way
what the truth really is there does seem
to be some wisdom in there
i mean our ancient wisdom has to be
taken very seriously yes of course
but in the 21st century our scientists
need to
take that wisdom and analyze it properly
and
quantify it and then demonstrate to the
world that our wisdom is indeed correct
so for for the example of the breathing
that you have given there are
contradictions definitely
like that like i said all these aquatic
mammals they breathe very less
very few times per minute they can hold
their breath for
a couple of hours at a time and yet they
don't live that long so there is clearly
a contradiction here
so what i would say about this is that
this in the
in the case of human beings we need to
investigate this properly and thoroughly
using science
ashutosh asks neil tyson says the
world's first trillionaire will come
from asteroid mining
who owns the wealth mind from asteroids
owner of the company or government or
the un
see it's like this right now you have uh
you have we are on the threshold of the
privatization of space
what that means is that you have these
private companies like spacex and
and virgin galactic and blue origin that
are
taking the that are currently at the
forefront of space exploration
yes they are beginning to venture into
commercialization of space
etc so in the next coming decades
you will see private companies being at
the forefront of this
now who owns this wealth the u.n is
irrelevant the un is a nobody or
it's an organ organization with no power
they have no jurisdiction anywhere
okay they are basically a stick that the
west uses to beat the rest of the world
with
when they choose the u.n is irrelevant
it is an organization of with no power
now who owns this wealth is it the owner
of the company
so in the future if spacex goes into
asteroid mining
will elon musk own all the wealth well
elon musk doesn't own the company he
owns maybe a share of the company
so by the time spacex if it does grow
that large
it will have a number of investors a
number of owners
it will have a number of hidden owners
and many of these owners will also be
owned by somebody else
so in the end it's always the most
powerful
group of people in the country which is
the government
it's always the government which has the
which holds the ultimate power
and every company no matter how wealthy
you are you are
you are basically under the control they
can change the laws anytime
they can exert that power in time so if
it is an american
company that is doing the asteroid
mining the wealth will belong
it will be under the control of the us
government
that's what it is so it is the overall
power structure that you have to see to
understand who owns the wealth
power always trumps wealth
harsh asks uh what do you think about
the future of
local space travel what do you think the
future of local space travel and tourism
will be
will it become feasible accessible in
popular form of travel on earth
in the light of virgin atlantic's
successful space flight demonstration
should the indian government take this
up as a near future project or should it
promote
private aerospace startups or companies
to take this up
think the indian government i think the
space tourism is going to really take
off
in the coming decade by the time this
decade is out
the 2020s i think space tourism will
become a regular feature
virgin galactic has taken the first step
in this space x will be
definitely doing this uh blue origin
will also be into space tourism
so these are us-based companies they
will earn a lot of money from the
rich people of the world from the
wealthy people of the world in space
tourism i mean who doesn't want to go up
into space
and see the curvature of the earth and
float around in zero gravity for a few
minutes
it is a great thrill and every wealthy
person will line up for this for sure
and soon you will have trips around the
moon as well which is going to start
happening in the next two or three years
space x will be i believe taking the
initiative in this
so this is definitely going to be a very
attractive form of tourism especially
for the wealthy class
for the wealthy people people who have a
few million dollars to spare
yeah it is not going to be uh accessible
to the ordinary middle class people of
the earth
not anytime soon not in the next 30 40
years maybe maybe in the next 30 40
years
or 50 years but as of now it's going to
be
the thrill of the wealthy people and
it's going to generate a lot of money
for the companies that do this should
the indian government get into this
i think the indian government should get
into strategic geopolitical scale
space exploration which means setting up
bases on the moon
on mars having space station having all
the capabilities
that every other country has and beyond
so india needs to take the lead
in space exploration from a strategic
and geopolitical perspective space
tourism should also
be encouraged in india but by private
players
so india needs to create an environment
that is conducive
for private companies to start making
their own rockets
and and starting a space tourism kind of
business as of today entrepreneurship is
very
hard in india the environment in india
is not conducive for entrepreneurship
we don't have any silicon valley kind of
setup anywhere
in the country it's very hard to be an
entrepreneur
it's very hard to be even a small
business person and
if you become bigger in business there
are all kinds of hardships and hurdles
that you have to
overcome bureaucratic policy level
hardships
that and roadblocks and all kinds of
uh problems that that any
business person faces and that's why big
business doesn't take off in india
uh you see i mean you see this you see
millions of examples of this
so as of today india doesn't have a
conducive
environment for this sort of business
so that is the job of the indian
government it needs to reform
the indian system make india business
friendly
especially encourage local businesses
using high technologies
to to create startups like these you
know space startups
i know there is one or two there are one
or two space startups in india
what have they achieved thus far how
many space launches have they been able
to do
so that is a state of of of of affairs
in this country
and that's what needs to change so the
government should not go itself into
space
tourism it should create the right
environment in the right
milieu for this sort of business
to emerge and prosper and flourish
in india
okay is the universe conscious
we don't know it could be but here's the
thing about consciousness
we are all conscious aren't we but we
are not conscious of what's happening
inside our brain we are conscious of the
external world
so our brain or our mind
is a conscious entity we associate
it with with our body because it is tied
to our body
and we are conscious of what's happening
external to our body
and external to our mind we don't know
what's happening in our subconscious
mind
we don't know what's happening in our
neurons in our brain we don't know
what's happening inside our body we can
have
we can sense we can sense the beating of
our heart
we can sense our lungs breathing and we
can sense certain other things
there is some feedback neuro feedback
etc but as far as the mind goes we are
conscious of nothing that's happening
internal to the mind
so consciousness is projected externally
we are conscious of what's outside
of the consciousness so if our universe
were conscious
and if it were similar to our
consciousness then it will be conscious
of something
external to it not something internal to
it
so in case our universe is conscious
it would it would not be conscious of us
who are basically
organisms living inside the universe it
would only be conscious of what lies
external to it so that would basically
uh uh work only if there's a multiverse
of sorts
so if there are other universes out
there if there are other worlds out
there and if our universe is conscious
then it could conceivably be conscious
of what's outside
so maybe we can ask the universe if we
can find a way of communicating with it
what's external to it that's an
interesting thought
so the answer is we don't know if it's
conscious
but it could be because if we look at
the large scale structure of the
universe
at the very large scales at kilo parsec
scales
thousands of light years then the
filamentary structure of the universe
the filaments that comprise these super
clusters of galaxies etc
the structure the filamentary structure
of the universe is exactly the same
as the neural structure of our brain so
it's it does
look like the internal structure of a
brain so
that's why people have conjectured that
the universe could be a conscious
organism on its own the question is that
how do thoughts uh
how how do thoughts form in this
conscious universe because in our in our
mind in our brain
thoughts are believed to be the result
of these
uh neural processes these
electrochemical signals that travel
between our neurons and that has a
certain speed right
now in the universe you have we know
there's a speed limit
the speed of light now it would take
hundreds of thousands or even millions
or even billions of light years for
these thoughts to actually occur
because of the enormous distance
distances that we know exist
in the observable universe so unless
there is something like wormholes or
traversable wormholes
or cosmic strings etc that could
possibly
help the universe think as a
consciousness in real time
but it's all hypothetical it's all
conjectural because we don't know
so to answer in short maybe it's
conscious but if it is conscious it may
not be conscious of
us it may be conscious of something that
lies external to it
okay ayosh asks almost all the ed
tech views show space time
curving below a planet or star like a
trampoline but there's no
top or bottom in space then does it mean
space time curves in all directions
around a planet or a star and
if so how can a black hole have infinite
curvature of space time
in all directions so the trampoline
analogy that is used in popular uh
science programs is just an analog
analogy
a trampoline is a three-dimensional
object
space-time is four-dimensional so we
cannot visualize four-dimensional space
time
because we are three-dimensional
creatures the world we live in
has only three dimensions right
we can only imagine or conceive of a
world that has three dimensions
so it is not possible for our gr for our
brain for our mind our consciousness
to imagine something in four dimensions
and that's why we use this
three-dimensional analogy
and therefore what does curvature and
four-dimensional space time look like
we don't know we can't imagine it that's
why we try to
replicate it in three dimensions so it
there is curvature but we don't know
we we don't know how to visualize it
because it is not possible
for us three-dimensional creatures to
visualize it but
mathematically there is indeed curvature
when it comes to black holes
and infinite curvature see this infinite
curvature of black holes the singularity
it is something that that arises out of
the equations of general relativity
from the mathematics of these equations
and in mathematics whenever you have a
singularity and infinity
it indicates that your equations are
faulty
so so this infinite curvature
that you get from these equations it
actually indicates that the equations
have broken down
at the ultra microscopic scale it tells
you that this theory this these
equations
they work only in the large scale
of the universe at large scales at
classical scales they don't work at the
microscopic and ultra microscopic scale
they don't work at the quantum scale and
that's why you get this infinity this
infinite curvature
most likely there is no infinite
curvature there's something else in
there
but we don't know what it is because we
have been thus far
unable to reconcile
general relativity with quantum
mechanics
so so the equations of general
relativity
don't work incur in
rather the equations of quantum field
theory
don't work in curved space time so these
two theories are as of today
they have not been reconciled and that's
why you get these
mathematical oddities like singularities
it means your theory has broken down at
a certain point
i'm sure there is no actual singularity
or infinity or infinite curvature
or infinite mass density
okay let's take a few live questions
do we have any live questions we have
lots of comments
live chat comments
oman asks does time exist for photons
as general relativity tells us the time
stops at the speed of light
how to be an astronomer physicist
etcetera what are its fusion which is
scope
see the second question is a long
question so i mean
there are lots of different explanations
so i'll answer your first question
does time exist for photons as general
relativity tells us that time
general relativity does not tell you
that time stops anywhere
okay that's the first thing secondly
photons are quantum mechanical particles
right and general relativity does not
apply
at the quantum scale so it appears that
time may not even
exist at the quantum scale
you know we don't know what time is time
is something we seem to sense
but we don't have a physical definition
of time we do use it in equations
we do use time derivatives we do use
time and graph etc
but we don't know what time is what is
time where does it emerge from
is it an emergent property of the
universe is it a local property of the
universe
is it something that is inherent to the
universe or is it something that arises
from the quantum scale
do you have molecules and atoms of time
or does time not even exist at the
quantum scale we don't know anything
about that
it may even appear that time may be an
illusion created by the decoherence
of quantum phenomena
so we don't know so we don't know if
time exists for photons
does time even have a meaning for a
photon
we don't know that time is the greatest
mystery we have in physics
and we are nowhere close into solving it
so time may be something that we
perceive
as something that emerges out of the
deco he as a result of d coherence
of quantum phenomena maybe that is what
time is maybe that is a dividing line
line between past present and future
maybe
we still don't know so it's an excellent
question but
that is one of the fundamental mysteries
that we are currently
grappling with in theoretical physics
suraj asks why is the indian government
not funding enough for space programs i
have not heard any minister
talking about space related programs why
does the younger generation end up
joining nasa when we have isro well why
do we
why does the government not fund space
because space doesn't have any priority
it is the farmers who have the priority
for our politicians
it is these employment generation
schemes
and various other populist measures that
get you votes
because elections are very important
votes are very
important you have to stay in power
right so that's where all the energy and
focus and
all the money goes now we have israel
and we have nasa so why does everybody
join want to join nasa
well what is the salary isro my friends
and what is the salary at nasa
how are you treated at isro by the
bureaucrats who run the organization
and how are you treated at nasa there's
a world of difference
right so that is the reason why
everybody
wants would prefer to join nasa because
you have
you are treated with much more respect
your status is much higher
your salary is several times more maybe
10 times 20 times more than you would
get ever get in israel
and you are not under the thumb of any
bureaucrat in nasa yet they have their
own bureaucracy but
it is a bureaucracy that actually is
interested in furthering the space
program and
empowering the scientists not and
keeping you down
like indian bureaucrats
[Music]
so that is the reason why nasa is far
more attractive than israel he said oh
it's a brilliant organization we have
the best scientists there
they have done so much but they are not
allowed to do what everything that they
can
they could develop much more powerful
rockets they could build a space station
they could send human beings to
to earth orbit to to they could
construct a base on the moon
and send human beings there we could
even send people in the next 20 years to
mars
if we were to empower israel but we have
to treat our scientists well
we have to make them feel like they are
valued and they are respected
we have to value them by giving them a
salary
that is internationally competitive
right so that they don't feel frustrated
and unhappy
and secondly we have to empower them
into doing what they can do best which
is
developing new technologies and doing
the best science they're capable of
so that is what is needed and that's
what's not happening and that's why nasa
is more attractive
than isro unfortunately even though
our young people they do want to do
something good for the country but
they are not allowed to they are not
allowed to
the system in india doesn't value
patriotism it doesn't value it doesn't
advance
talent it advances mediocrity that is
the system we are living in that is what
needs to be
changed and the government is thus far
not doing any of that
because has there been any any reform in
the bureaucracy of india in the past
any significant reform in india's
bureaucracy
in living memory no so that's why
nothing is changing
okay let me take one more question
something interesting
sanskrit or tamil i have answered that
question and it's not science my friend
today it is about science
okay let me find some interesting
question
can diamonds be created artificially
from coal by giving enough temperature
and pressure yes it is done
routinely in labs
uh
okay let's take this question by
divyansh how does the flowing core
of the earth generate a magnetic field
around the earth
can a huge moon also have its own
magnetic field
if the earth were a moon of jupiter it
would have its own magnetic field yes
so how is the earth's magnetic field
generated so the interior of the earth
is composed of molten it's mostly iron i
think it's all metal
at an extremely high pressure and a very
high temperature
and at this temperature and because of
the conditions
that exist so far so deep inside
below the earth's surface this intense
pressure this intense heat
so that is what causes these electric
charges
to swirl around in the interior of this
metal because metals
conduct electricity and you have free
electrons in metal especially in molten
metal etcetera
so that's what causes these electric
electric currents and fields inside the
earth
and whenever you have a moving charge
you have a magnetic field so it is this
molten inter interior this molten
metal iron interior of the earth
that generates the magnetic field that
we have and it is this magnetic field
that
enables us to stay alive because it
shields us
from all the cosmic radiation and the
solar wind and everything
which is extremely harmful to human life
and
all other life on the planet so that is
how
the magnetic field that is how in short
in simple
words how the internal structure of the
of the earth generates the magnetic
field that protects us
and it's one of the reasons why we have
a thick atmosphere because
the magnetic field of the of mars for
example has has
more or less died out and because of
that all this bombardment by the solar
wind and cosmic rays
has stripped away the atmosphere of mars
and
it's become very very uh the atmosphere
has become quite sparse
compared to the atmosphere on earth
so it is one of the reasons why the
atmosphere has become sparse it's one of
the reasons why all the
water that once flowed on mars has
evaporated
away and that's the reason why mars has
become so barren
and dry at least on the surface
so yes so that's how earth gen the earth
generates its magnetic field
and yes a huge moon can indeed have its
own magnetic field if it is large enough
to have a molten metallic
internal structure okay my friends
we are done for today thank you very
much for your questions thank you for
watching
and i will see you very soon in the next
episode this time we have a new topic
education
so i look forward to seeing you there
but for today i wish you a good day a
good night and
see you next time bye